Guide to the Knights of Equity Court #9 Records, 1938-1977 AIS.1977.36
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Knights of Equity Court #9 Records
1936-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Knights of Equity. Court #9 (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1977.36
3 microfilm_reels
The Knights of Equity, Court 9, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records consist of the constitution, minute books, programs, a scrapbook, and photographs for the period 1936-1977.
History
The Knights of Equity is one of America's oldest Irish-Catholic organizations. The Knights were first organized to protect Irish immigrants from violence that was directed towards them upon their arrival in America. According to their Articles of Incorporation the object of the Knights of Equity was "to create and foster a spirit of mutual helpfulness among its members; to advance them intellectually and socially; and by cooperation among them to promote their material interests and well-being." The Knights of Equity formed as a secret body for men with the following qualifications: Irish heritage, Roman Catholic, over the age of 21, and a resident of the city where a Knights of Equity had an office.
The Pittsburgh Section of the Knights of Equity was founded in 1895, known to the National Section as Court 9. The local Knights of Equity are known for their celebration of St. Patrick's Day and their contributions to many local Irish and Roman Catholic causes.
Scope and Content Notes
The Knights of Equity Records span the years 1936-1977. This collection includes the constitution and by-laws, record books, programs, a scrapbook, correspondence, photographs, and miscellaneous items. The bulk of the information in this collection concerns Court 9, but there are materials relating to the National Section and the Daughters of Erin, a group started by the wives and sisters of members of the Knights of Equity in 1959. The first reel contains copies of the Constitution and by-laws from 1947 and revised versions from 1969 and 1977, as well as correspondence from many of the Court 9 officers. In reel 2 there is a continuation of the correspondence and many of the programs for the St. Patrick's Day celebrations. The last reel contains materials for National Conventions, a scrapbook, and photographs. The photographs, however, do not contain names, dates, or locations.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were microfilmed by the Archives Service Center, with permision, in 1977.
Existence and Location of Orginals
Originals are retained by Knights of Equity Court #9.
Previous Citation
Knights of Equity Court #9 Records, AIS.1977.36, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Knights of Equity Court 9, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, AIS Micro 77:39, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Genealogy; Societies; Human rights -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Ethnic groups; Social justice; Social action; Irish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Discrimination against Irish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Knights of Equity. Court #9 (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Constitution and by-laws, revisions, 1948, 1969, 1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
- Supreme Council record book, Volume 1, 1896 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
- Supreme Council record book, Volume 2, 1960-1970 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
- Bicentennial Committee, Minutes, 1975-1976 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
- Programs, 1943-1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  General note
  Includes St. Patrick's Day Banquet and Dance (1943) and Degree Banquet (October 25, 1964)
- St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1974 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  Letter concerning which Irish group in Pittsburgh founded the parade. The Knights of Equity were the founders according to this letter.
- National Convention, Minutes, Volume 1, 1964-1969 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
- National Convention, Minutes, Volume 2, 1970-1976 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
- National Convention, Programs, 1938, 1948, 1960-1975 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
- National Convention, Mayor Barr's Speech, 1968 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
- Mini-Conventions, 1973-1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
- Scrapbook, 1941-1969 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
- Articles of Incorporation, Irish Club of Pittsburgh, 1949 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
- Irish Press Corporation, 1936-1938 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
- Photographs (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
- Miscellaneous Publications, 1947-1972 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
  Includes Short History of Knights of Equity, Court 9, 1968-1971 by John McMahon